<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Datatype SYSTEM "../DTD/Datatype.dtd">
<Datatype>
	<KnowledgeBase>
        <Title>LongVector</Title>
		<Type>Heap</Type>
		<RelatedTypes>BitVector CpxVector NumVector FloatVector Vector ObjVector 
                      IntVector PcodeVector</RelatedTypes>
		<HumanKeywords>Heap Vectors LongVector Element Array</HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
	<Section>                
	    <Heading>LongVector Overview</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
        <p> A <b>Long Vector</b> <i>(ShortVector)</i> is a Heap object containing zero or more 32 bit integer data values.
        Assuming there are n elements in a vector, the elements of the vector are accessed 
        as elements 0 thru n-1. An <b>LongVector</b> also has a tail in the same sense that a 
       Pair has a tail.</p>
            <p> This sets an LongVector of four integer values.
                </p>
            <p>(setq X (new Vector:  Long: 4 5 2 11 6)) </p>
             <table align="center" border=4 cellspacing=5 cellpadding=5>
               <tr><td>5</td> </tr>
               <tr><td>2</td> </tr>
               <tr><td>11</td> </tr>
               <tr><td>6</td> </tr>
           </table>    
          <p>The <b>LongVector</b> is a dynamic data type: it can grow to containing new elements 
             or contract as elements are deleted as long as it does not exceed its limit 
             of 32 bit integer data values.    An element is accessed by an index from 0 
             to n-1 where n is the number of elements in the <b>IntVector</b>.   When an element is added, 
             it is appended to the end.</p> 
          <table align="center" border=4 cellspacing=5 cellpadding=5>
               <tr><td>5</td> </tr>
               <tr><td>2</td> </tr>
               <tr><td>11</td> </tr>
               <tr><td>6</td> </tr>
               <tr><td>4</td> </tr>
           </table> 
           <p>Or we might sort the vector</p> 
           <table align="center" border=4 cellspacing=5 cellpadding=5>
               <tr><td>2</td> </tr>
               <tr><td>4</td> </tr>
               <tr><td>5</td> </tr>
               <tr><td>6</td> </tr>
               <tr><td>11</td> </tr>
           </table> 
           <p>Or we might delete a key by specify the index of the item to be deleted (2)</p> 
           <table align="center" border=4 cellspacing=5 cellpadding=5>
               <tr><td>2</td> </tr>
               <tr><td>4</td> </tr>             
               <tr><td>6</td> </tr>
               <tr><td>11</td> </tr>
           </table>
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
	<Section>                
	    <Heading>When to Use</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
          <p>The <b>LongVector</b> is a subtype of the Vector Data Type. The 
            LongVector object is useful for storing integers.
            The LongVector object is very fast 
            and has minimum memory overhead due to the indexed access of its values.  If you 
            require a random access strategy or a keyed access strategy see the Dictionary or 
            Structure data types.  </p>
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
	<Section>                
	    <Heading>Visual Basic Comparison</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
          <p>An Analytic Information Server <b>LongVector</b> is similar to the single dimensioned dynamic 
            array in Visual Basic. The Visual Basic array is created at compile time (the Visual Basic 
            Array still requires a "ReDim" to specify a dimension), whereas the Analytic Information Server 
            structure is created, expanded, or contracted dynamically at run time. </p>
          <p><b>Dim DayArray(50)</b></p>
          <p>DayArray is an array of Variants with 51 elements indexed, from 0 thru 50.</p>
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
	<Section>                
	    <Heading>Constant Form</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
          <p>The <b>LongVector</b> native data type has a constant form. A <b>LongVector</b> constant is enclosed 
             in brackets and preceded by the sharp symbol #(long| ).  </p>
          <p>For Example:</p>
          <p><b>#(long| 5 2 11 6 4)</b></p>
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
	<Section>                
	    <Heading>Object Data Types</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
          <p>The <b>LongVector</b> is a Heap Object or an Object Data Type. The Analytic Information Server Object Types 
            are stored in the Heap and are managed by the Heap manager.  The Analytic Information 
            Server Heap manager supports object resizing, garbage collection, and anti-fragmentation algorithms 
            so that the user may concentrate on the analysis and modeling of data rather than on
            memory management. Without exception, all of the Object types are identified by an 
            object id.  The object id identifies a block of memory, managed by the Lambda 
             Information Server memory manager, in which the Object's data is stored.</p>
         <p>The Analytic Information Server Heap Object and Native Data types can be saved and loaded to and from persistent
            (disk file) storage at any time. Containers with immediate data are saved on disk 
            in fixed length records equal to the size of the container. Containers with Heap 
            object references are saved in fixed length records, which are automatically expanded 
            to include the contents of the Heap object, and any objects referenced by the Heap 
            object, etc. This feature is called Object Closure Management and is automatic with 
            every Analytic Information Server container database save.</p>
         <p>Analytic Information Server containers may be loaded from any database repository record 
            at any time. If the data in the record is immediate, the database load fills the 
            container with the immediate data. If the data in the record is an object closure, 
            the database load fills the container with a Heap object reference, and all of the 
            objects in the record are loaded back into the Heap with the same referential 
            relationships they had when they were saved in the repository.</p>    
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
</Datatype>
