<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Datatype SYSTEM "../DTD/Datatype.dtd">
<Datatype>
	<KnowledgeBase>
        <Title>Structure</Title>
		<Type>Heap</Type>
		<RelatedTypes>Dictionary Vector Directory</RelatedTypes>
		<HumanKeywords>Heap Key Value Element Array</HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
	<Section>
	    <Heading>Structure Overview</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
         <p class=MsoBodyText>A Structure is a table with two columns. The
          left column contains symbolic keys, and the right column contains the value
           associated with its respective symbolic key.</p>
			<p class=MsoBodyText>A Structure has a variable number of rows;
			however, a Structure always has exactly two columns (the symbolic keys and the
			values associated with those symbolic keys). Both the keys and values are
			available at run time, and the Structure can be sorted by keys or values, can
			have keys added, altered, or deleted dynamically. </p>        
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
	<Section>
	    <Heading>Structure Illustration</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
        <p> A Structure Object is analogous to a table containing exactly two columns and an 

            arbitrary number of rows.  The left column contains a key (must be an Object type:

            Symbol, List, Pair , any Vector type, Structure, Dictionary, Repository, or  Lambda ) 

            , and the right column contains the value associated with its key. Any given row 

            in a table is analogous to a Structure binding of a Key/Value pair.</p>
               <table align="center" border=4 cellspacing=5 cellpadding=5>
               <tr><td>Name</td> <td>John Doe</td> </tr>
               <tr><td>Salary</td> <td>$55000</td>  </tr>            
               <tr><td>Address</td> <td> 184 Anywhere St.</td>  </tr>      
               <tr><td>City</td> <td>Los Angeles</td> </tr>   
               <tr><td>State</td> <td>California</td> </tr>               
           </table>    
          <p>We can sort the structure by key in descending order. Using the Structure above,
              the resulting sorted structure is: </p>
              <table align="center" border=4 cellspacing=5 cellpadding=5>    
               <tr><td>State</td> <td>California</td> </tr>     
               <tr><td>Salary</td> <td>$55000</td>  </tr>   
               <tr><td>Name</td> <td>John Doe</td> </tr>
               <tr><td>City</td> <td>Los Angeles</td> </tr>           
               <tr><td>Address</td> <td> 184 Anywhere St.</td>  </tr>                                        
           </table>    
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
	<Section>
	    <Heading>When to Use</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
          <p>Structures  are convenient for storing 

             Key/ Value pairs in unsorted order. They have a relatively small overhead  compared to 
             Dictionaries or Directories which sorts these key value pairs automatically.   </p>
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
	<Section>
	    <Heading>Visual Basic Comparison</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
          <p>An Analytic Information Server Structures are similar to the user-defined type of 

           Visual Basic. The Visual Basic user defined type is created at compile time, 

           whereas the Analytic Information Server structure is created, expanded, or contracted 

           dynamically at run time. The main difference is that the Visual Basic user defined 

           type is static and the Analytic Information Server structure is dynamic, and the object keys offer a 

           wider range of values.</p>
          <p><b>Type Employee</b></p>
          <p><b>Name  As Variant   <blockquote>' Name of the employee.  </blockquote>  </b></p>
          <p><b> Salary As Variant    <blockquote>' Salary  of the employee.  </blockquote>  </b></p>
           <p><b>Address   As Variant   <blockquote>' Address  of the employee.  </blockquote>  </b></p>
           <p><b>City   As Variant   <blockquote>' City  of the employee.  </blockquote>  </b></p>
           <p><b>State   As Variant   <blockquote>' State  of the employee.  </blockquote>  </b></p>
         <p><b>End Type</b></p>
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
	<Section>
	    <Heading>Constant Form</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
          <p>The Structure data type supports a simple constant form. 
             The whole Structure constant is enclosed in braces and preceded by the sharp symbol and a left-brace (<b>#{ ... }</b>) and terminated with a right-brace. 
             Some Structure constant examples: 
             </p>
          <p><b>#{Name: "John Doe"  Address: "184 Anywhere Street" City: "Los Angeles" State: "California"}</b></p>
    
          <p>The constant form for Structures allows embedded Analytic Information Server objects for the values or keys as follows:
             </p>

          <p><b>#{X:  5  Y:  #{Mike: "father"  Sally: "mother"}  Z:  "Hello"}</b></p>
          <p><b>#{Date: #Jan,1 ,1972  Manager: #{Name: "Joe Smith" Age: "45"}  Employee: #{Name: Jan Brown Address: "28"}}</b></p>

          <p>The Structure data type also supports a strongly-typed declarative form. 
             The declarative Structure constant is enclosed in braces and preceded by the sharp symbol, a left-brace, and the decl notation (<b>#{decl| ... }</b>), and terminated with a right-brace. 
             Some declarative Structure constant examples: 
             </p>

          <p><b>#{decl| (String:Name "John Doe") Number:Salary}</b></p>
    
          <p><B>Note:</b> The declarative constant form, shown above, supports the same variable declaration and initialization syntax as in 
             the <b>args:()</b>, <b>vars:()</b>, <b>svars:()</b>, <b>pvars:()</b>, and <b>cvars:()</b> sections of the <b>lambda</b> special form.
             See the <b>lambda</b> special form for additional information on variable declaration.
             </p>


        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
	<Section>                
	    <Heading>Object Data Types</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
          <p>The <b>Structure</b> is a Heap Object or an Object Data Type. The Analytic Information Server Object Types 
            are stored in the Heap and are managed by the Heap manager.  The Analytic Information 
            Server Heap manager supports object resizing, garbage collection, and anti-fragmentation algorithms 
            so that the user may concentrate on the analysis and modeling of data rather than on
            memory management. Without exception, all of the Object types are identified by an 
            object id.  The object id identifies a block of memory, managed by the Lambda 
             Information Server memory manager, in which the Object's data is stored.</p>
         <p>The Analytic Information Server Heap Object and Native Data types can be saved and loaded to and from persistent
            (disk file) storage at any time. Containers with immediate data are saved on disk 
            in fixed length records equal to the size of the container. Containers with Heap 
            object references are saved in fixed length records, which are automatically expanded 
            to include the contents of the Heap object, and any objects referenced by the Heap 
            object, etc. This feature is called Object Closure Management and is automatic with 
            every Analytic Information Server container database save.</p>
         <p>Analytic Information Server containers may be loaded from any database repository record 
            at any time. If the data in the record is immediate, the database load fills the 
            container with the immediate data. If the data in the record is an object closure, 
            the database load fills the container with a Heap object reference, and all of the 
            objects in the record are loaded back into the Heap with the same referential 
            relationships they had when they were saved in the repository.</p>    

         <p><b><font color="red">NOTE:</font></b> The <b>Structure</b> is a special type in AIS Lisp. 
            Structures are used to store the strongly-typed templates for all class variables,
            persistant variables, constant variables, and temporary variables.
            In addition, strongly-typed user-defined Structure templates can be declared using the declarative constant form of the Structure.
            </p>

        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
</Datatype>
