<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Datatype SYSTEM "../DTD/Datatype.dtd">
<Datatype>
	<KnowledgeBase>
        <Title>Directory</Title>
		<Type>Heap</Type>
		<RelatedTypes>Structure Vector Dictionary</RelatedTypes>
		<HumanKeywords>Heap Key Value Element Array</HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
	<Section>                
	    <Heading>Directory Overview</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
        <p> A Directory is an object that is very similar to a Dictionary.  Analytic Information Server 
        Dictionary Objects and Directory objects share common properties: they both contain an arbitrary 
        number of bindings, values can be referenced by key, or a single index, or two, and keys are 
        always maintained in ascending sort order.</p>
        <p>The only difference between a Directory and a Dictionary is they type of keys a Directory 
        can have.  A Directory key can be <b>ANY</b> Analytic Information Server type: native types as well 
        as Object Types such as Symbol (Unquoted or Quoted), List, Pair (Unquoted or Quoted), all Vector 
        types, Structure, Dictionary, Repository, or Lambda. </p>
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
	<Section>                
	    <Heading>Directory Illustration</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
        <p> A Directory Object is analogous to a table containing exactly two columns and an 
        arbitrary number of rows.  The left column contains a key (must be any Analytic Information 
        Server Native or Object type: Symbol, List, Pair, any Vector type, Structure, Dictionary, 
        Repository, or Lambda), and the right column contains the value associated with its key. 
        Any given row in a table is analogous to a Dictionary binding: Key/Value pair.</p>
               <table align="center" border=4 cellspacing=5 cellpadding=5>
               <tr><td>#Jan,1,1996</td> <td>"Meeting with J.R. Mummy"</td> </tr>
               <tr><td>#Jan,12,1996</td> <td>"Budget Deadline"</td>  </tr>
               <tr><td>#Jan,19,1996</td> <td>"Demo Product X"</td> </tr>
               <tr><td>#Jan,23,1996</td> <td> "Leave for Boston"</td>  </tr>
           </table>
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
	<Section>                
	    <Heading>When to Use</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
          <p>Directories are like Dictionaries, in that they are convenient for storing Key/ Value pairs. 
           However, they have a maintenance overhead required for saving a richer universe of keys. 
            An application that requires sorted Object keys would be more efficient by using a Dictionary. </p>
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
	<Section>                
	    <Heading>Constant Form</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
          <p>The Directory native data type supports a constant form. The whole Directory 
            constant is enclosed in braces and preceded by the sharp symbol, brace, and the 
           dir| symbol (<b>#{dir|</b>). Some Directory constant examples: </p>
          <p><b>#{dir| Name:  "John Doe"  Address: "184 Anywhere Street" City: "Los Angeles" State: "California"}</b></p>
    <p>The constant form for Directories allows using the constant prefix,  <b>#{dir||</b> with two bars, to specify 
             creating "as is" in unsorted order as follows:</p>
          <p><b>#{dir|| Z:  5  Y:  #{Mike: "father"  Sally: "mother"}  X:  "Hello"}</b></p>
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
	<Section>                
	    <Heading>Object Data Types</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
          <p>The <b>Directory</b> is a Heap Object or an Object Data Type. The Analytic Information Server Object Types 
            are stored in the Heap and are managed by the Heap manager.  The Analytic Information 
            Server Heap manager supports object resizing, garbage collection, and anti-fragmentation algorithms 
            so that the user may concentrate on the analysis and modeling of data rather than on
            memory management. Without exception, all of the Object types are identified by an 
            object id.  The object id identifies a block of memory, managed by the Lambda 
             Information Server memory manager, in which the Object's data is stored.</p>
         <p>The Analytic Information Server Heap Object and Native Data types can be saved and loaded to and from persistent
            (disk file) storage at any time. Containers with immediate data are saved on disk 
            in fixed length records equal to the size of the container. Containers with Heap 
            object references are saved in fixed length records, which are automatically expanded 
            to include the contents of the Heap object, and any objects referenced by the Heap 
            object, etc. This feature is called Object Closure Management and is automatic with 
            every Analytic Information Server container database save.</p>
         <p>Analytic Information Server containers may be loaded from any database repository record 
            at any time. If the data in the record is immediate, the database load fills the 
            container with the immediate data. If the data in the record is an object closure, 
            the database load fills the container with a Heap object reference, and all of the 
            objects in the record are loaded back into the Heap with the same referential 
            relationships they had when they were saved in the repository.</p>    
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
</Datatype>
