<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Datatype SYSTEM "../DTD/Datatype.dtd">
<Datatype>
	<KnowledgeBase>
        <Title>Complex</Title>
		<Type>Object</Type>
		<RelatedTypes>Void Error Character Integer Number Money Percent String 
		             Text Character</RelatedTypes>
		<HumanKeywords>Heap Complex Real Imaginary </HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
	<Section>                
	    <Heading>Complex Overview</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
		<p class=MsoBodyText>The Analytic Information Server engine supports complex numbers as a pair of real 
		values representing the real and imaginary parts of the complex number, respectively.  A complex number 
		is not a native type.  Rather, it is a heap object since two real numbers is too large to fit into the 
		space allotted to native types.  All of the standard operations on complex numbers 
		(add, subtract, multiply, divide, mod, sin, cos, tan, etc.) are supported.  In addition, several 
		built-in functions that are specific to complex numbers (real, imaginary, complex, conjugate, argument, modulus) 
		are also provided.</p>  
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
	<Section>                
	    <Heading>When to Use</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
          <p class=MsoBodyText>Use complex numbers for those functions that require complex number support.</p>         
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
    <Section>                
	    <Heading>Constant Form</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
			  <p class=MsoBodyText>Complex numbers are represented by a pair of floating-point numbers, representing the 
			  real and imaginary parts of the complex value.  For example:</p> 
			  <p><b> #C(3.14 2.718)</b></p>
			  <p>  If the second element is omitted, the imaginary value is set to <b>0.0</b>.</p>
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
 	<Section>                
	    <Heading>Object Data Types</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
          <p>The <b>Complex</b> is a Heap Object or an Object Data Type. The Analytic Information Server Object Types 
            are stored in the Heap and are managed by the Heap manager.  The Analytic Information 
            Server Heap manager supports object resizing, garbage collection, and anti-fragmentation algorithms 
            so that the user may concentrate on the analysis and modeling of data rather than on
            memory management. Without exception, all of the Object types are identified by an 
            object id.  The object id identifies a block of memory, managed by the Lambda 
             Information Server memory manager, in which the Object's data is stored.</p>
         <p>The Analytic Information Server Heap Object and Native Data types can be saved and loaded to and from persistent
            (disk file) storage at any time. Containers with immediate data are saved on disk 
            in fixed length records equal to the size of the container. Containers with Heap 
            object references are saved in fixed length records, which are automatically expanded 
            to include the contents of the Heap object, and any objects referenced by the Heap 
            object, etc. This feature is called Object Closure Management and is automatic with 
            every Analytic Information Server container database save.</p>
         <p>Analytic Information Server containers may be loaded from any database repository record 
            at any time. If the data in the record is immediate, the database load fills the 
            container with the immediate data. If the data in the record is an object closure, 
            the database load fills the container with a Heap object reference, and all of the 
            objects in the record are loaded back into the Heap with the same referential 
            relationships they had when they were saved in the repository.</p>    
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
</Datatype>
