<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Datatype SYSTEM "../DTD/Datatype.dtd">
<Datatype>
	<KnowledgeBase>
        <Title>Number</Title>
		<Type>Native</Type>
		<RelatedTypes>Void Boolean Character Integer Error Money Percent String 
		             Text Character</RelatedTypes>
		<HumanKeywords>Native Number Money Percent  </HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
	<Section>                
	    <Heading>Number Overview</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
		 <p class=MsoBodyText>Analytic supports the <b>Number</b> data type for representing various numeric values.  
		 The Number data type has three subtypes: Integer, Money, and Percent.  The Number data type and all of its 
		 subtypes can be extended by using the addMethod and defmethod  functions.</p>
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
	<Section>                
	    <Heading>When to Use</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
          <p>The Number Native data type is a suitable container for numeric values.  
          Several mathematical functions are provided by Analytic Information Server that perform several 
          common computations.</p>          
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
    <Section>                
	    <Heading>Number Subtypes</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
		<p><b>Integer    </b></p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText>The Integer Native Data Type are containers
		for whole numbers only. An Integer is a 32 bit integer value. The constant
		form for Integers are simple the number:</p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText><b style='mso-bidi-font-weight:normal'>34        -34 </b></p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText><b style='mso-bidi-font-weight:normal'><u>&nbsp;</u></b></p>
		<p><b>Money       </b>     </p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText>The Money Data Type are containers for
		monetary values.  Money is an IEEE double precision real number representing U.S. currency values. Money constants can be
		written as signed whole numbers or signed fractions starting with the $
		symbol.   Normal arithmetic can be
		performed on the Money Data Type.</p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText>&nbsp;</p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText><b style='mso-bidi-font-weight:normal'>$-4.56               $1845               $345.89            $-192745           </b></p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText><b style='mso-bidi-font-weight:normal'>&nbsp;</b></p>
		<p><b>Percent               </b></p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText style='line-height:117%;page-break-after:avoid'>The
		Percent Data Type are containers for
		percentage values. Percent constants can be written as signed whole
		numbers or signed fractions ending with the % symbol. </p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText style='line-height:117%;page-break-after:avoid'>&nbsp;</p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText style='line-height:117%;page-break-after:avoid'><b style='mso-bidi-font-weight:normal'>2%                   -34%                .02%                1.28%</b></p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText style='line-height:117%;page-break-after:avoid'>&nbsp;</p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText style='line-height:117%;page-break-after:avoid'>Terminating
		a numeric constant with the percent operator has the effect of dividing the
		constant by 100.</p>      
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
    <Section>                
	    <Heading>Constant Form</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
		<p class=MsoBodyText>The Number Data and all of its subtypes have
		constant forms.  The Number Data type
		can be represented by scientific notation such as:</p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText><b style='mso-bidi-font-weight:normal'>&nbsp;</b></p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText><b style='mso-bidi-font-weight:normal'>1.2e8
		               -4.567e-34</b></p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText>&nbsp;</p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText>or as a real number:</p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText>&nbsp;</p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText><b style='mso-bidi-font-weight:normal'>-345.8907         3.141592</b></p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText><b style='mso-bidi-font-weight:normal'>&nbsp;</b></p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText>or as a whole number:</p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText><b style='mso-bidi-font-weight:normal'>&nbsp;</b></p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText><b style='mso-bidi-font-weight:normal'>34        -34 </b></p>
		<p class=MsoBodyText><b style='mso-bidi-font-weight:normal'><u>&nbsp;</u></b></p>  
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
      <Section>                
	    <Heading>Native Data Type</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
          <p>The <b>Number</b> Data Type is an example of an AIS Native Data Type. </p>
          <p> Analytic Information Server stores all of its Native Data Types in Virtual Machine Containers.  
          All containers are stored in memory. Containers provide the basic storage mechanism for modeling 
          data of all types. Containers provide these fundamental characteristics:      </p>
          <p>  Ability to hold any type of data (including code) at any time.</p>     
          <p>  Ability to know what type of data is contained.</p>  
          <p>  Ability to be stored, retrieved and evaluated by the system.</p>  
          <p>   Ability to handle type conversion, and memory management automatically.</p>   
          <p> Containers come in two sizes, Large and Small. Small containers are six bytes in length, 
          and large containers are ten bytes in length. Large containers can store larger amounts of data 
          immediately and place less of a burden on the Heap manager. Small containers require less immediate space, 
          but place more of a burden on the Heap manager.    </p>        
          <p>  Large containers can store the following data types immediately and does not require the services of the Heap manager:</p>  
          <ul>
          <li> #void</li>  
          <li> error</li>
          <li> Boolean</li>
          <li> Character</li>
          <li> Integer</li>
          <li> Number</li>
          <li> Money</li>
          <li> Percent</li>
          <li> String</li>
          <li> Text</li>
          <li> Character</li>
          <li> ...heap object references...</li> 
          </ul>                             
          <p>  Small containers can store the following data types immediately without placing additional burden on the Heap manager:</p>  
          <ul>
          <li> #void</li>  
          <li> error</li>
          <li> Boolean</li>
          <li> Character</li>
          <li> Integer</li>
          <li> Number</li>
          <li> Money</li>
          <li> Percent</li>
          <li> String</li>
          <li> Text</li>
          <li> Character</li>
          <li> ...heap object references...</li> 
          </ul>           
          <p>  Analytic Information Server containers can be saved and loaded to and from persistent (database) 
          storage at any time. Containers with immediate data are saved on disk in fixed length records equal 
          to the size of the container. Containers with Heap object references are saved in fixed length records, 
          which are automatically expanded to include the contents of the Heap object, and any objects referenced 
          by the Heap object, etc. This feature is called Object Closure Management and is automatic with every 
          Analytic Information Server container database save. Analytic Information Server containers may be loaded 
          from any database repository record at any time. If the data in the record is immediate, the database 
          load fills the container with the immediate data. If the data in the record is an object closure, the 
          database load fills the container with a Heap object reference, and all of the objects in the record 
          are loaded back into the Heap with the same referential relationships they had when they were saved.</p>   
        ]]></Description>
    </Section>
</Datatype>
