<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Essay SYSTEM "../DTD/Essay.dtd">
<Essay>
	<KnowledgeBase>
	    <Title>RefGuide Introduction</Title>
		<Topic>AIS RefGuide</Topic>
		<SubTopic>AIS Documentation</SubTopic>
		<HumanKeywords>RefGuide Documentation </HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
	<Section>
	    <Heading>Overview</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[		
		    <div class="h2section" id="Overview">
		    <p>The Analytic Information Server Reference Guide Document Manager agect acts as a semi-intelligent document 
		     manager Lambda which is able to generate cross referenced and cross indexed 
             HTML documents in the specified input(Foundry) and output folder(wwwroot).</p>
            <p> The following are the list of folders in RefGuide: </p>
            <p><b>Foundry: </b> This is the specified input folder.  This folder contains the files the user needs
		     to generate the HTML Documents.  The file contents of the Foundry folder are evaluated
		     by the program aisRefGuide to generate the output. </p>
		    <p><b>wwwroot: </b> This folder contains the output of the aisRefGuide program. The ouput are
		     cross referenced and cross indexed HTML Documents. These ouput files
		     are saved in the output folder wwwroot.   </p>    
		     <p><b>CoreContent: </b> This contains all the input files needed to generated the AIS Documentation. </p>   
		     <p><b>Templates: </b> This  contains the Templates for the output HTML Pages. Each 
		     <a href="#Ontologies">Ontology Object</a> has a different Template.    
		     <p><b>Bin: </b>   The aisRefGuide Database file is store in this folder. </p>
		     <p><b>Source: </b> This contains the aisRefGuide source code saved as an  LambdaBase file (*.sl).
		      
		      <p> To generate the AIS Documentation, copy and paste all the files in CoreContent and Templates to
		      the Foundry folder.  These files in the Foundry folder will be the files evaluated by aisRefGuide.
		    		     
		    </div>
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section>
	<Section>
	    <Heading>Ontologies</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
		    <div class="h2section" id="Ontologies">  
		    An <a name="Ontologies">ontology</a> is a description of the concepts and relationships that can exist for an Lambda or a community of Lambdas.  
		    The aisRefGuide main Lambda and its other child Lambdas operate on a defined set of Ontology Objects.  These Ontology Objects
		    specify a specific knowledge grouping used in AIS.  These knowledge groupings represented as Ontology Objects (or Ontologies)
		    are as follows:

		           <p><b>Document Ontologies:</b>   These contain a list of Essay Ontologies.  A Document Ontology defines
		                  the structure of an AIS Document.     </p>       
		              <p> See an example of a  <a href="Essay_RefGuide_Ontology_Examples.html#SDocument Ontology" > Document Ontology</a>.   </p>   
		           <p><b>Essay Ontologies:</b> These contain paragraphs, tables and images that relate to a 
		                  specifiec topic not classfied by any other Ontology.      </p>            
		              <p>  See an example of an <a href="Essay_RefGuide_Ontology_Examples.html#SEssay Ontology" >Essay Ontology</a>.  </p>   
		           <p><b>Datatype Ontologies:</b> These have informatation on the different Datatypes used in
		                  AIS programming. </p>     
		               <p>See an example of a  <a href="Essay_RefGuide_Ontology_Examples.html#SDatatype Ontology" >  Datatype Ontology</a>.  </p>    
		           <p><b>Function Ontologies: </b> These contain information on AIS Functions.  Function Information mainly
		                        includes Syntax and Usage.   </p>
		                <p>  See an example of a <a href="Essay_RefGuide_Ontology_Examples.html#SFunction Ontology" > Function Ontology</a>.  </p> 
                   <p><b>Example Ontologies:</b> These represent Source Code Examples  to illustrate AIS Functions.  </p>
		               <p>  See an example of an <a href="Essay_RefGuide_Ontology_Examples.html#SExample Ontology" > Example Ontology</a>.  </p>     
		          <p><b>VMInstruction: </b> These contain information in AIS Virtual Machine Instructions. Like Function
		                       Ontologies,  VMInstruction Ontologies mainly include Syntax and Usage.  </p>  
		               <p>  See an example of a <a href="Essay_RefGuide_Ontology_Examples.html#SVMInstruction Ontology" >  VMInstruction Ontology </a>.  </p>
		         <p><b>Note:</b>  Ontology attributes represented in XML are used to cross reference and cross index AIS Ontologies. </p>
		  </div>
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section>
</Essay>
