<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Essay SYSTEM "../DTD/Essay.dtd">
<Essay>
	<KnowledgeBase>
	    <Title>AIS New Help Home</Title>
		<Topic>AIS</Topic>
		<SubTopic>Analytic Information Server</SubTopic>
		<HumanKeywords>AIS Lisp Programming Artificial-Intelligence</HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
	<Section>
	    <Heading>Introducing: Analytic Information Server&amp;trade</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
			<P>
			Analytic Information Server&trade;(AIS) is an analytic database designed to store massive amounts of heterogeneous data, 
			upon which complex computer science algorithms are to be employed.  
			The goal is to convert data, whose information content is a mystery, into data whose information content is understood.
			</P>
			<P>
			The principle component of data analysis is the "Lambda". 
			AIS is a database designed specifically for the easy storing and retrieval of Lambdas. 
			AIS Lambdas are Internet aware programs, which are Internet mobile across copies of the AIS engine. 
			Upon execution, within an instance of the AIS engine, 
			Lambdas execute at near native machine register speeds - greatly exceeding the execution speeds of C programs.
			</P>
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section>
	<Section>
	    <Heading>Internet Services</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
			<P>
			Each instance of the AIS engine attaches to a user defined TCP/IP port, 
			making each instance of the AIS engine a web analytic server. 
			AIS Lambdas can serve their analytic reports directly to a web browser or to any other program, 
			which can open a TCP/IP connection. Pure HTML, XML, or a proprietary binary protocol is supported; 
			and, each of these protocols can be used to invoke individual Lambdas residing on available AIS engines. 
			Furthermore, Lambdas in one instance of the AIS engine can invoke Lambdas in any other available AIS engine connected by TCP/IP. 
			Each instance of the AIS engine can support multiple Lambda contexts, each running on its own machine thread.
			</P>
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section>
	<Section>
	    <Heading>Fast Virtual Machine</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
			<P>
			AIS supports an ultra-fast register virtual machine with a proprietary Just-In-Time compiler (JIT). 
			The AIS virtual machine is designed to support fast algorithm development as well as ultra-fast algorithm execution. 
			The VM accommodates these two design goals by supporting four well-defined instruction sets.
			</P>
			<ul>
				<li>1.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Generic Instructions for rapid algorithm development (which execute at 1/10th the speed of C).</li>
				<li>2.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Native Instructions (which execute at near the speed of C).</li>
				<li>3.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Register Instructions (which execute at 3 to ten times the speed of C). </li>
				<li>4.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Vector Processor Instructions (which execute at 7 to fifteen times the speed of C).</li>
			</ul>
			<P>
			AIS Lambda development begins with the generic instructions until the algorithm "proof of concept" is attained 
			followed by conversion of the bottleneck routines into native, register, or vector instructions for ultra-fast algorithm execution.
			The AIS JIT's drawback is Lambda bloat. 
			A great deal more information is saved about each Lambda than in a standard C binary program executable. 
			This is not a terrible problem, since AIS is a high volume database, the data size dwarfs any possible code bloat. 
			Another drawback is that Lambda invocation runs at approximately 50% of the speed of C function invocation 
			- more information means there is a longer set up time to invoke an Lambda than a C binary function. 
			This is not a terrible problem, since most ultra-fast algorithms must be code generated in linear layout, 
			without too many embedded function calls, to avoid cache hits. For extremely fast algorithm execution, 
			algorithms should fill up registers, L1, L2, and L3 cache with as few interruptions as possible.
			</P>
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section>
	<Section>
	    <Heading>How does Analytic Information Server&amp;trade work?</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
			<P>
			AIS supports an ultra-fast register virtual machine with a proprietary Just-In-Time compiler (JIT). 
			The AIS virtual machine is designed to support fast algorithm development as well as ultra-fast algorithm execution. 
			The VM accommodates these two design goals by supporting four well-defined instruction sets.
			</P>
			<ul>
				<li>1.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Generic Instructions for rapid algorithm development (which execute at 1/10th the speed of C).</li>
				<li>2.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Native Instructions (which execute at near the speed of C).</li>
				<li>3.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Register Instructions (which execute at 3 to ten times the speed of C). </li>
				<li>4.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Vector Processor Instructions (which execute at 7 to fifteen times the speed of C).</li>
			</ul>
			<P>
			AIS Lambda development begins with the generic instructions until the algorithm "proof of concept" is attained 
			followed by conversion of the bottleneck routines into native, register, or vector instructions for ultra-fast algorithm execution.
			The AIS JIT's drawback is Lambda bloat. 
			A great deal more information is saved about each Lambda than in a standard C binary program executable. 
			This is not a terrible problem, since AIS is a high volume database, the data size dwarfs any possible code bloat. 
			Another drawback is that Lambda invocation runs at approximately 50% of the speed of C function invocation 
			- more information means there is a longer set up time to invoke an Lambda than a C binary function. 
			This is not a terrible problem, since most ultra-fast algorithms must be code generated in linear layout, 
			without too many embedded function calls, to avoid cache hits. For extremely fast algorithm execution, 
			algorithms should fill up registers, L1, L2, and L3 cache with as few interruptions as possible.
			</P>
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section> 
	<Section>
	    <Heading>Analytic Information Server&amp;trade Engine Architecture</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
			<P>
			Analytic Information Server&trade; supports multiple concurrent users, transaction rollback with no arbitrary 
			limitation on the size of a transaction, password protected data security with automatic record 
			compression and encryption, data recovery, and a runtime dynamic database schema at each location.
			</P>
			<P>
			AIS is agnostic concerning programming paradigms, virtual machines, and programming languages. 
			AIS provides a built-in AIS Lisp compiler. Multiple virtual machines are supported, 
			in fact a parent Lambda can run on one virtual machine while its child Lambda can run on another. 
			Also, an Lambda can serve as a virtual machine for any other Lambda. 
			There is built-in support for functional programming, object oriented programming, rule based programming, and Lambda oriented programming. 
			Also supplied is an AIS JavaScript compiler, and an AIS HTML/XML compiler.
			</P>
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section>
	<Section>
	    <Heading>Adaptive Intelligence: Why You Need It</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
			<P>
			AIS technology represents a significant step forward in the use of  "Intelligent Lambdas" 
			in integrating both existing and new distributed applications with "Adaptive Intelligence".
			Adaptive Intelligence allows applications to identify previous patterns and relationships 
			in a user's interaction history and then use this new information to alter the application's 
			responses for a more effective, personal user experience. It's the key to retaining customers 
			and ensuring a greater share of their business over time by developing personalized relationships.  
			Increased knowledge about users quickly translates to better customer service, more opportunities 
			to cross sell services and products, and ultimately improved results.
			</P>
			<P>
			An application with a personalized, responsive interface is compelling. People will 
			return to a Web site which is different with each visit. Static web pages bore people. 
			Students proceed at a faster rate when the application reconfigures as the person learns. 
			Data mining is more accurate when the mining application adapts to feedback results. 
			Kids retain interest in games which constantly reconfigure to match the player's skill 
			level and past game experiences.
			</P>
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section>
	<Section>
	    <Heading>Built-in Functions</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
			<P>
			Here are links to AIS Built-in Functions grouped according to Data Type.
			</P>
			<P>
			<!--docscript>(aisRefGuide.functionLinkTable)</docscript-->
			</P>
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section>
	<Section>
	    <Heading>Built-in Object</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
			<P>
			Here are links to the functions of the AIS Built-in Objects.
			</P>
			<P>
			<!--docscript>(aisRefGuide.dataTypeLinkTable)</docscript-->
			</P>
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section> 
	<Section>
	    <Heading>Virtual Machine Instructions</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
			<P>
			AIS Lambdas are designed to be write-once-run-anywhere executable objects. 
			This is accomplished via the virtual machine concept of software Lambda execution. 
			Lambda virtual machines are designed to be mapped onto the actual host microchip at the server location, 
			providing faithful Lambda execution wherever the Lambda may travel on the Internet. 
			There are currently several virtual machines operating within Analytic Information Server. 
			The DRM virtual machine uses a Dynamically typed Register Machine model to provide portable Lambda execution 
			from high level dynamically typed instructions all the way to super fast microchip-level register execution. 
			The DRM virtual machine runs in emulation mode during the testing and debug phases of Lambda development, 
			and there is an AIS Lambda debugger available for Lambdas running on this virtual machine. 
			During the final release phases of Lambda development, DRM virtual machine Lambdas are automatically converted 
			to the NATIVE virtual machine on the host computer, using the just-in-time compiler. 
			The NATIVE virtual machine is a faithful machine language translation of the execution rules in the DRM virtual machine 
			onto the actual host microchip at the server location. 
			NATIVE virtual machine execution runs at microchip-level execution speeds.
			</P>			
			<P>
			<!--docscript>(aisRefGuide.vmLinkTable)</docscript-->
			</P>
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section>
</Essay>
