<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Function SYSTEM "../DTD/Function.dtd">
<Function>
	<KnowledgeBase>
        <Title>stdev</Title>
		<FunctionName>stdev</FunctionName>
		<FunctionType>Builtin(Math)</FunctionType>
		<ArgumentTypes>Number Integer </ArgumentTypes>
		<DataType>Number</DataType>
		<RelatedFunctions>range kurtosis skew stdevp var</RelatedFunctions>
        <RelatedVMInstructions> none  </RelatedVMInstructions>
		<HumanKeywords>standard deviation distribution curve sample displacement mean </HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
         <Description><![CDATA[
             <p> The <b>stdev </b> function computes the standard deviation of a population based on a sample 
              of values specified in the argument list.</p>
          ]]></Description>
	<Brief>
	   <Overview><![CDATA[
		 <p> The <b>stdev</b> function computes the standard deviation of a population based 
           on a sample of values specified in the argument list. Standard deviation measures 
          the spread or dispersion of values from the mean. It is the same as the square root
          of the variance of the population sample.</p>
        ]]></Overview>
        <Usage><![CDATA[
        <p>The <b>stdev</b> function is suitable for calculating the standard deviation 
         on a sample of values for a population. The formula for calculating the standard 
         deviation of a sample is different from the formula for calculating the standard 
         deviation of the population, though for large numbers of values (greater than 50) 
        the difference between the two calculations is very small. If your data values 
        represent an entire population rather than a sample, use the stdevp function to 
        calculate the standard deviation
         </p>
         ]]></Usage>
    </Brief>
	<Syntax>
	    <Expression><![CDATA[   (stdev num1 num2 ...)]]></Expression>
		<Argument>
		  <Name>num1 num2... </Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>Any number of values</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Number</AISTypes>
		</Argument>
		<Return><![CDATA[
	    <p>Returns the standard deviation of a population based on a sample of values
         specified in the argument list
	    </p>
	    ]]></Return>
	</Syntax>
</Function>
