<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Function SYSTEM "../DTD/Function.dtd">
<Function>
	<KnowledgeBase>
        <Title>mod</Title>
		<FunctionName>mod</FunctionName>
		<FunctionType>Builtin(Math)</FunctionType>
		<ArgumentTypes>Number Integer</ArgumentTypes>
		<DataType>Number Complex</DataType>
		<RelatedFunctions>  imod div  modi (sym)div</RelatedFunctions>
        <RelatedVMInstructions> vmiadd vmidiv vmidivr vmimul   </RelatedVMInstructions>
		<HumanKeywords> number arithmetic division mod remainder number operators </HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
         <Description><![CDATA[
             <p> The <b>mod</b> function divides two numbers and returns the remainder. 
</p>
             <p> The <b>mod</b> function computes the remainder from the 
             ratio of the real parts of the arguments. </p>                
          ]]></Description>
	<Brief>
	   <Overview><![CDATA[
		<p>The <b>mod</b> function divides two numbers and returns the remainder. The <b>mod</b> 
          function performs an integer divide, but the result is type Number (See Native Types).
        </p>
        ]]></Overview>
	   <Overview-Complex><![CDATA[
		<p>The <b>mod</b> function computes the remainder from the ratio of the real parts of 
          the arguments. The modulo of two complex numbers is:</p>
        <p>(xr &#43 i xi) mod (yr &#43 i yi) = xr &#37 yr
        </p>
        ]]></Overview-Complex>
        <Usage><![CDATA[
        <p>The <b>mod</b> function is analogous to the remainder function in other systems.
           It is useful for determining if a number will divide evenly into another number 
           (the remainder will be zero in this case).
        </p>
        <p>If either argument is complex, only the real part is used in the computation.
        </p>
         ]]></Usage>
        <Usage-Complex><![CDATA[
        <p>The <b>mod</b> function is used to find the remainder of the ratio of two numeric 
         data types where at least one of the arguments is complex. The modulo function is not 
         widely used in any of the statistical or numerical analysis routines.
        </p>
       ]]></Usage-Complex>
    </Brief>
	<Syntax>
	    <Expression><![CDATA[<p><b>(mod dividend divisor)    </b></p>
]]></Expression>
		<Argument>
		  <Name>dividend</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>The number to be divided (will be converted to an integer before divide)</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Number</AISTypes>
		</Argument>
		<Argument>
		  <Name>divisor</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>Divide by this number (will be converted to an integer before divide)</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Number</AISTypes>
		</Argument>
		<Return><![CDATA[
	    <p>The remainder after computing an integer divide. The result is expressed as a number.

	    </p>
	    ]]></Return>
	</Syntax>
</Function>
