<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Function SYSTEM "../DTD/Function.dtd">
<Function>
	<KnowledgeBase>
        <Title>systemCheck</Title>
		<FunctionName>systemCheck</FunctionName>
		<FunctionType>Builtin</FunctionType>
        <ArgumentTypes> Boolean  </ArgumentTypes>
        <DataType> Context </DataType>
	    <RelatedFunctions>preAllocateFixedMemoryBlocks debug inspect</RelatedFunctions>
        <RelatedVMInstructions> none  </RelatedVMInstructions>
		<HumanKeywords>context system check debug</HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
         <Description><![CDATA[
             <p>The <b>systemCheck</b> function performs a system diagnostic check of the
             current memory manager and displays a system error message if any memory blocks 
             are damaged and cannot be repaired.   </p>
          ]]></Description>
	<Brief>
	   <Overview><![CDATA[
	    <p>The <b>systemCheck</b> function performs a system diagnostic check of the current 
         memory manager and displays a system error message if any memory blocks are damaged 
         and cannot be repaired. If there are no arguments, the <b>systemCheck</b> function 
         displays the low-level memory manager allocations according to frame size and displays
         some basic statistics on memory usage. If there is a single argument, and it is false, 
         then the <b>systemCheck</b> function does NOT display memory statistics on the console. If 
         there is a second argument, and it is boolean (true or false), then the Analytic Information 
         System engine system-self-check-mode is set on (true) or off (false). In system-self-check-mode,
         a system check is performed a frequent intervals. This greatly reduces execution speed; 
         but, is useful in tracking sown elusive error conditions. </p>
        ]]></Overview>
       <Usage><![CDATA[
       <p>Use the <b>systemCheck </b> function to perform a system diagnostic check and to view
        the memory usage of the Analytic Information Server System. The systemCheck function is 
        useful for determining if there are memory leaks. As a debugging aid, the <b>systemCheck</b>
        function is useful also to determine if invalid or damaged objects are created by the 
        Analytic Information Server System. </p>
        ]]></Usage>
    </Brief>
	<Syntax>
	    <Expression><![CDATA[<p><b>      (systemCheck) </b></p>
                    <p><b>      (systemCheck displaySW) </b></p>
                    <p><b>      (systemCheck displaySW selfCheckSW)  </b></p>
]]></Expression>
		<Argument>
		  <Name>displaySW </Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p> (Optional) A boolean argument which, if missing or true, causes memory
            block statistics to be displayed on the AIS console during system self check. </p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Boolean</AISTypes>
		</Argument>   
		<Argument> 
		  <Name>selfCheckSW</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p> (Optional) A boolean argument which causes the Analytic Information System 
          engine system-self-check-mode is be set on (true) or off (false). </p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Boolean</AISTypes>
		</Argument>
		<Return><![CDATA[
	    <p>The Boolean value, true.</p>
	    ]]></Return>
	</Syntax>
</Function>
