<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Function SYSTEM "../DTD/Function.dtd">
<Function>
	<KnowledgeBase>
        <Title>objectToMatrix</Title>
		<FunctionName>objectToMatrix</FunctionName>
		<FunctionType>Builtin</FunctionType>
        <ArgumentTypes> Vector NumVector List Matrix Structure 
                        Dictionary Directory Integer Real Number Complex </ArgumentTypes>
        <DataType>   Matrix </DataType>
	    <RelatedFunctions>new  objectToNumMatrix </RelatedFunctions>
        <RelatedVMInstructions> vmregObjPointer </RelatedVMInstructions>
		<HumanKeywords>convert numvector vector elements dimensional planes</HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
         <Description><![CDATA[
             <p> The <b>objectToMatrix</b> function converts the object 

                 into a Matrix returning the new Matrix.   </p>
          ]]></Description>
	<Brief>
       <Overview><![CDATA[
       	<p>The <b>objectToMatrix</b> function converts the object <b>{object}</b> into a 

            Matrix returning the new Matrix.  The <b>{object}</b> may be a List, Vector, 

            Matrix, Structure, Dictionary, or a Directory.  If the object is already a 

            Matrix, it is returned unchanged.  If it is any other type of Matrix 

            (e.g., NumMatrix), it is converted into a regular matrix.  A Vector is converted into 
            a Matrix.  An object vector containing vectors is converted into a two-dimensional 
            matrix.  Each of these vectors is converted to one row of the matrix.  An object 
            vector containing object vectors that each contain a vector is converted into a 
            three-dimensional matrix.  Each of these object vectors contains one plane of the 
           matrix (first dimension).  Each plane is converted into rows as described above for 
          two-dimensional matrices.  Several examples are shown below.</p>
        <p>If a vector is being converted, an optional rank and the dimensions of the resulting 
           matrix may be specified.  If no rank is provided, the vector is converted to a 
            one-dimensional matrix.</p>
        ]]></Overview>
	   <Usage><![CDATA[
		<p>The <b>objectToMatrix</b> function is used to convert a Vector, List, Matrix, 

           Structure, Directory or Dictionary object to a Matrix object. </p>
        ]]></Usage>
    </Brief>
  <Syntax>
	    <Expression><![CDATA[<p><b>  (objectToMatrix   object rank dim1 dim2 dim3) </b></p> ]]></Expression>
    	<Argument>
		  <Name>obj</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>A Vector, List, Matrix, Structure, Dictionary or Directory Object</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Vector List Matrix Structure 
                     Dictionary Directory  </AISTypes>
		</Argument>
   	    <Argument> 
		  <Name>rank</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>Optional.  Rank of the resulting matrix (1, 2, 3)</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Integer </AISTypes>
		</Argument>
  	    <Argument> 
		  <Name>dim1</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>Optional.  Size of the first dimension of the resulting matrix</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Integer </AISTypes>
		</Argument>
  	    <Argument> 
		  <Name>dim2</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>Optional.  Size of the second dimension of the resulting matrix</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Integer </AISTypes>
		</Argument>
  	    <Argument> 
		  <Name>dim3</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>Optional.  Size of the third dimension of the resulting matrix</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Integer </AISTypes>
		</Argument>
		<Return><![CDATA[
	    <p>A Matrix object</p>
	    ]]></Return>
	</Syntax>
</Function>
