<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Function SYSTEM "../DTD/Function.dtd">
<Function>
	<KnowledgeBase>
        <Title>count</Title>
		<FunctionName>count</FunctionName>
		<FunctionType>Builtin</FunctionType>
		<ArgumentTypes>Structure Integer Character Number Symbol Text String Boolean
NumMatrix
                   List Pair Vector Dictionary Directory Matrix </ArgumentTypes> 
		<DataType>Structure Dictionary Directory Vector Matrix Pair List  NumMatrix</DataType>
		<RelatedFunctions>length</RelatedFunctions>
        <RelatedVMInstructions> vmregObjLength   </RelatedVMInstructions>
		<HumanKeywords>count length values deep shallow</HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
         <Description><![CDATA[
             <p> The <b>count</b> function returns the number of values in the object argument. </p>
          ]]></Description>
	<Brief>
	   <Overview><![CDATA[
		<p>The <b>count</b> function returns the number of values in the object argument <b>{obj}</b>.  
           If <b>{obj}</b> is a collection object, such as a List, Vector, Structure, Matirx, Dictionary, or 
           Directory, the <b>count</b> function performs a <i>deep</i> count, i.e., all items in 
           any imbedded collection objects are also counted. </p>
        ]]></Overview>
        <Usage><![CDATA[
        <p>Use the <b>count</b>function to determine the total number of items in an object, 
           including the items in imbedded collection objects.  This type of counting is called a 
           deep count. An alternate type of counting is called a shallow count in which embedded 
           collection objects are counted as one.  An alternate function, the <b>length</b> 
           function, performs a shallow count. </p>
        ]]></Usage>
    </Brief>
	<Syntax>
	    <Expression><![CDATA[<p>(count obj)</p>]]></Expression>
		<Argument> 
		  <Name>obj</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>Any Analytic Information Server object</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Structure Integer Character Number Symbol Text String Boolean
                   List Pair Vector Dictionary Directory Matrix </AISTypes>
		</Argument>
		<Return><![CDATA[ 
	    <p>If the target is #void, character, number, symbol, text, string, or Boolean, 
           the value 1 is returned. <br>
           If the target is a List, then the number of Pairs in the list is returned.<br>
           If the target is a Vector, then the number of items in the vector is returned.<br>
           If the target is a Structure, Dictionary, or Directory, then the number of bindings is returned.
           If the target is a Matrix, then the number of non-void items is returned.
        </p>
	    ]]></Return>   
	</Syntax>
</Function>
