<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Function SYSTEM "../DTD/Function.dtd">
<Function>
	<KnowledgeBase>
        <Title>checkPointTransaction</Title>
		<FunctionName>checkPointTransaction</FunctionName>
		<FunctionType>Builtin</FunctionType>
        <ArgumentTypes>ObjectRepository Boolean</ArgumentTypes>
        <DataType> ObjectRepository</DataType>
	    <RelatedFunctions> beginTransaction abortTransaction commitTransaction </RelatedFunctions>
        <RelatedVMInstructions> none  </RelatedVMInstructions>
		<HumanKeywords>persistent transaction </HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
         <Description><![CDATA[
             <p> The <b>checkPointTransaction </b> function closes the specified ObjectRepository database archive file  
             and marks the end of a series of transactions. </p>
          ]]></Description>
	<Brief>
	   <Overview><![CDATA[
		<p>The <b>checkPointTransaction</b> function closes the specified ObjectRepository database
         archive file <b>{aGor}</b> and marks the end of a series of transactions. When a <b>beginTransaction</b>
         function is evaluated, the ObjectRepository treats all transactions as temporary until either of the 
         <b>abortTransaction</b>, <b>checkPointTransaction</b>, or <b>commitTransaction</b> functions are evaluated.
         If an <b>abortTransaction</b> function is evaluated, all objects stored in the ObjectRepository, 
         up to the previous <b>beginTransaction</b>, are rolled back; however, if a <b>checkPointTransaction</b> 
         or a <b>commitTransaction</b> function is evaluated, all objects stored in the ObjectRepository,
         up to the previous <b>beginTransaction</b>, are made persistent. </p>
        ]]></Overview>
        <Usage><![CDATA[
         <p>The <b>checkPointTransaction</b> function leaves the ObjectRepository with the current 
         transaction still in progress. The <b>checkPointTransaction</b> function is equivalent to 
         invoking a <b>commitTransaction</b> function immediately followed by another <b>beginTransaction</b>
          function. </p>
        ]]></Usage>
    </Brief>
    <Syntax>
	    <Expression><![CDATA[<p>(checkPointTransaction aGor)  </p>]]></Expression>
		<Argument>
		  <Name>aGor</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p> The ObjectRepository whose database archive file is to be closed, then re-opened again.</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>ObjectRepository</AISTypes>
		</Argument>
		<Return><![CDATA[
	    <p>This function returns the Boolean value true, or an error value if an error occurred. 
	    ]]></Return>
	</Syntax>
</Function>
