<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Function SYSTEM "../DTD/Function.dtd">
<Function>
	<KnowledgeBase>
        <Title>isIdentical</Title>
		<FunctionName>isIdentical</FunctionName>
		<FunctionType>Builtin</FunctionType>
    	<ArgumentTypes>Character String Symbol Vector BitVector ByteVector ShortVector IntVector Function
                       FltVector ObjVector Structure Dictionary Directory Brick Pair List
                       Matrix NumMatrix Integer Float Number Complex Void Error Boolean Date ObjectRepository
                       FltVector IntVector NumVector ObjVector  BitVector PcodeVector </ArgumentTypes>
        <DataType> Matrix Structure Dictionary Directory Vector Brick Pair Function ShortVector NumMatrix Character List Void Error Boolean Number Date Complex ObjectRepository FltVector IntVector NumVector ObjVector  BitVector PcodeVector</DataType>
		<RelatedFunctions>compareEQ comparison isEqual</RelatedFunctions>
        <RelatedVMInstructions>vmregObjPointer  </RelatedVMInstructions>
		<HumanKeywords>  Equal Analytic Object Identical</HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
          <Description><![CDATA[ 
             <p> The <b>isIdentical</b> function compares the two arguments to see if they identical. </p>
          ]]></Description>
	<Brief>
       <Overview><![CDATA[
		<p>The <b>isIdentical</b> function compares the two arguments to see if they identical. 
        If the arguments are both native data objects, the immediate values are compared to see 
        if they are equal, in which case, the <b>isIdentical</b> function returns a Boolean value 
        of <b>true</b> otherwise it returns <b>false</b>.  If the arguments are both heap data 
        objects, the object Ids are compared to see if they are equal, in which case, the 
        <b>isIdentical</b> function returns a Boolean value of <b>true</b> otherwise it returns <b>false</b>. 
        </p>
		<p>The <b>==</b> relational operator calls the <b>isIdentical</b> function to perform its comparison. 
        </p>
        ]]></Overview>
        <Usage><![CDATA[
        <p>Use the <b>isIdentical</b> function when you wish to compare two Objects to 
          determine if they are identical (they are one and the same).
        </p>
        ]]></Usage>
    </Brief>
	<Syntax>
	    <Expression><![CDATA[<p>    (isIdentical obj1  obj2 )</p>]]></Expression>
		<Argument>
		  <Name>obj1</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>First object to be compared.</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Structure Dictionary Directory Vector Character Function NumMatrix ShortVector
                 Boolean Brick Matrix Pair List Void Error Number Date Complex</AISTypes>
		</Argument>
    	<Argument>
		  <Name>obj2</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p> Second object to be compared.</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Structure Dictionary Directory Vector Brick Function NumMatrix ShortVector
                  Boolean Matrix Pair List Void Error Character Number Date Complex</AISTypes>
		</Argument>
		<Return><![CDATA[
	    <p>For Native Data Types, returns true if the immediate values are identical and returns false if otherwise.
           For
Heap Data Objects, returns true of the Object Ids are identical and returns false if otherwise.
        </p>
	    ]]></Return>
	</Syntax>
	<Syntax-ObjectRepository>
	    <Expression><![CDATA[<p>    (isIdentical arg1 arg2 )</p>]]></Expression>
		<Argument> 
		  <Name>arg1</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>First Repository  to be compared.</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>ObjectRepository</AISTypes>
		</Argument>
    	<Argument> 
		  <Name>arg2</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p> Second Repository to be compared.</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>ObjectRepository</AISTypes>
		</Argument>
		<Return><![CDATA[ 
	    <p>This function returns the Boolean value true if the Repository Ids are equal; Returns
             false if the Repository Ids are not equal.
        </p>
	    ]]></Return>   
	</Syntax-ObjectRepository>
</Function>
