<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Function SYSTEM "../DTD/Function.dtd">
<Function>
	<KnowledgeBase>
        <Title>lambda</Title>
		<FunctionName>lambda</FunctionName>
		<FunctionType>Special Form</FunctionType>
		<ArgumentTypes>Lambda</ArgumentTypes>
		<DataType>Lambda</DataType>
		<RelatedFunctions>setq defun eval argCount argFetch makeLambda</RelatedFunctions>
        <RelatedVMInstructions>  none  </RelatedVMInstructions>
		<HumanKeywords>lambda evaluated compile </HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
         <Description><![CDATA[
             <p> The <b>lambda </b> special form returns an instance of a Lambda object. </p>
          ]]></Description>
	<Brief>
	   <Overview><![CDATA[
		<p>The <b>lambda</b> special form returns an instance of a Lambda object.  When called, the Lambda 
         extends its environment to include the specified argument variables <b>{arg}</b>, the arguments are 
         received and bound to the proper variables <b>{arg}</b>, the expressions <b>{exp}</b> are evaluated 
         from left to right, and the value of the final expression is returned.       </p>
        <p>
An Analytic Information Server Lambda may be defined, with a definite list (fixed) or an indefinite 
         list of arguments <b>(variable)</b>. The ellipses at the end of the argument list indicate the function 
         has indefinite arguments. At run time, the Lambda's actual arguments are bound to the specified formal 
         definite arguments respectively. An error is generated if there are too few arguments in the definite
         argument list.  If the number of actual arguments exceed the number of definite arguments, and the 
        function has been defined as having indefinite arguments, the excess arguments can only be accessed 
        during via the <b>argCount</b> and <b>argFetch</b> functions at run time. </p>
        <p>The keyword <b>faces:(var...)</b>  declares the interfaces feature Structure of the Lambda.  
         The features are specified as lists,  <b>faces:((english  true) (french  false))</b>,  the listed 
         feature is initialized to the value specified.</p>
      <p>The keyword <b>vars:(var...)</b>  declares the temporary variables of the Lambda.  The variables are 
         specified as follows  <b>vars:(X  Y...)</b>.  If any one of the variables is specified as a list, 
         <b>vars:((X  0)  Y...)</b>,  the listed variable is initialized to the constant value specified. 
         (The variable X is initialized to the constant 0). Unlike the setq or define special forms, the vars 
         special form always evaluates the initialization value as a constant.</p>
      <p>The keyword <b>pvars:(var...)</b>  declares the persistent variables of the Lambda.  The variables are 
         specified as a list  <b>pvars:(W  Q...)</b>.  If any one of the variables is specified as a list,  
         <b>pvars:((X  0)  Y...)</b>,  the listed variable is initialized to the constant value specified. 
        (The variable X is initialized to the constant 0). Unlike the setq or define special forms, the pvars 
        special form always evaluates the initialization value as a constant.</p>
      <p>The keyword <b>cvars:(var...)</b>  declares the persistent class variables of the Lambda.  The variables are 
        specified as a list  <b>cvars:(W  Q...)</b>.  If any one of the variables is specified as a list,  
        <b>pvars:((X  0)  Y...)</b>,  the listed variable is initialized to the constant value specified. 
        (The variable X is initialized to the constant 0). Unlike the <b>setq</b> or <b>define</b> special forms, 
        the cvars special form always evaluates the initialization value as a constant.</p> 
      <p>The keyword <b>rvars: (var...)</b>  declares the register variables of the Lambda.  The variables are 
        specified as a list <b>rvars: (W  Q...)</b>.   If any one of the variables is specified as a list, 
        <b>regs:  ((X  Integer)  Y...)</b>,  the listed variable is initialized to the type value specified 
        <i>(Integer, Number, CharPointer, ShortPointer, JumpPointer, IntPointer, or NumPointer)</i>.  
        The variable X is initialized to the data type Integer  <i>(up to fifty register variables are allowed)</i>. 
        Unlike the <b>cvars</b> or <b>pvars</b> special forms, the <b>regs</b> special form always evaluates 
        the initialization value as a data type.</p>
      <p>The body of the Lambda is a sequence of Lisp expressions <b>{exp}</b>. At run time, each of the 
        expressions is evaluated, in the extended environment, from left to right.  The Lambda returns the value
         of the final expression in the sequence. </p> 
  ]]></Overview>
        <Usage><![CDATA[
        <p>Use the <b>lambda</b> special form when an Lambda is to be created in Lisp. The Lambda is not 
           assigned to a global variable as with the defun macro.</p>
         ]]></Usage>
    </Brief>
	<Syntax>
	    <Expression><![CDATA[ <b>  (lambda(arg...)  faces:(var...) vars:(var...)  pvars:(var...)  cvars:(var...)  
               regs:(var...)  exp...)</b>]]></Expression>
		<Argument> 
		  <Name>(arg...)</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p> Optional Argument. Argument list for the Lambda. </p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>---</AISTypes>
		</Argument>   
		<Argument> 
		  <Name>faces:(var...)</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p> Optional Argument. If present, must be followed by a interfaces feature list. </p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Symbol</AISTypes>
		</Argument>  
		<Argument> 
		  <Name>vars:(var...)</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p> Optional Argument. If present, must be followed by a local variable list.</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Symbol</AISTypes>
		</Argument>  
		<Argument> 
		  <Name>pvars:(var...)</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p> Optional Argument. If present, must be followed by a persistent variable list.</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Symbol</AISTypes>
		</Argument>  
		<Argument> 
		  <Name>cvars:(var...)</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p> Optional Argument. If present, must be followed by a persistent class variable list.</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Symbol</AISTypes>
		</Argument>  
		<Argument> 
		  <Name>regs:(var...)</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p> Optional Argument. If present, must be followed by a register variable list 
              (up to fifty register variables are allowed).</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Symbol</AISTypes>
		</Argument>  
		<Argument> 
		  <Name>exp...</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p> The Lisp statements that forms the Lambdas</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>---</AISTypes>
		</Argument>  
		<Return><![CDATA[ 
	    <p>An Lambda object.</p>
	    ]]></Return>
	</Syntax>
</Function>
