<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Function SYSTEM "../DTD/Function.dtd">
<Function>
	<KnowledgeBase>
        <Title>fileDisplay</Title>
		<FunctionName>fileDisplay</FunctionName>
		<FunctionType>Builtin(FileIO)</FunctionType>
		<ArgumentTypes>ByteVector Text Integer Boolean </ArgumentTypes>
		<DataType>ByteVector  Text</DataType>
		<RelatedFunctions>fileOpen fileClose fileRead fileWrite writeln display fdisplay </RelatedFunctions>
        <RelatedVMInstructions> none   </RelatedVMInstructions>
		<HumanKeywords> file fileID display ASCII</HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
         <Description><![CDATA[
             <p> The <b>fileDisplay</b> function converts the expression   to ASCII text and writes the text
              value of the expressions to the specified fileID.  The <b>fdisplay</b> function is a deprecated
              version of the <b>fileDisplay</b> function. </p>
          ]]></Description>
	<Brief>
	   <Overview><![CDATA[
		<p>The <b>fileDisplay</b> function converts the expression <b>{exp}</b> to ascii text and 
          writes the text value of the expressions to the specified fileID <b>{fileID}</b>. 
          The fileID must be assigned from a previous fileOpen function. The <b>fileDisplay</b>
         function always returns a Boolean value <b>true</b>.</p>
        ]]></Overview>
        <Usage><![CDATA[
        <p>Data is written to a file with the <b>fileWrite, fileWriteln, fwriteln, fdisplay or fileDisplay </b> functions, 
         however, records are not actually <i>committed</i> to the file until the file is closed. 
         Thus, attempting to read a record immediately after a <b>fileWrite, fileWriteln, fwriteln, fdisplay or fileDisplay </b>
         will result in an error. In order to verify records that have been written, it is 
         necessary to close the file and save the file (<b>fileClose</b> with an option argument
          equal to 1) . The file can then be re-opened and read with the <b>fileRead</b> function.</p>
        ]]></Usage>
    </Brief>
	<Syntax>
	    <Expression><![CDATA[<p>(fileDisplay fileID exp)</p>]]></Expression>
		<Argument> 
		  <Name>fileID</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>An Integer representing the fileID of the file which was opened with a fileOpen function.</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Integer</AISTypes>
		</Argument>
		<Argument> 
		  <Name>exp</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>An expression</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>String Text ByteVector  </AISTypes>
		</Argument>
		<Return><![CDATA[ 
	    <p>Always the Boolean value, true.
        </p>
	    ]]></Return>   
	</Syntax>
</Function>
