<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Function SYSTEM "../DTD/Function.dtd">
<Function>
	<KnowledgeBase>
        <Title>replace</Title>
		<FunctionName>replace</FunctionName>
		<FunctionType>Builtin</FunctionType>
		<ArgumentTypes> String Text Integer</ArgumentTypes>      
		<DataType>String  </DataType>
		<RelatedFunctions>substitute rept</RelatedFunctions>
        <RelatedVMInstructions>none</RelatedVMInstructions>
		<HumanKeywords>replace substitute substring</HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
         <Description><![CDATA[ 
             <p> The <b>replace</b> function replaces a specified number of characters 
                 in a Text or String with another Text or String.  </p>
          ]]></Description>
	<Brief>                
	   <Overview><![CDATA[
		<p>The <b>replace</b> function replaces a specified number of characters in a 
        Text or String with another Text or String.  The <b>replace</b> function is 
        non-destructive
        </p>
        ]]></Overview>
        <Usage><![CDATA[
        <p>The <b>replace</b> function replaces only the substring at the specified index.  
           The <b>replace</b> function is similar to the <b>substitute</b> function, except 
           that <b>substitute</b> can replace any or all of the occurrences of the specified 
           substring whereas <b>replace</b> only replaces one at a specified position in the 
           String. </p>
        ]]></Usage>
    </Brief>
	<Syntax>
	    <Expression><![CDATA[<p><b>(replace old-text start length new-text)</b></p>
              ]]></Expression>
		<Argument> 
		  <Name>old-text</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>A String object or Text that contains the text to be replaced. </p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>String or Text</AISTypes>
		</Argument>  
    	<Argument> 
		  <Name>start</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>A positive integer indicating the position of the first character in old-text to be replaced.
              Set start to 0 for the first character, 1 for the second and so on</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Integer</AISTypes>
		</Argument>  
    	<Argument> 
		  <Name>length</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>A positive integer representing the number of characters, after the starting 
             position, to be replaced.  </p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Integer</AISTypes>
		</Argument>  
        <Argument> 
		  <Name>new-text</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>The Text or String to be inserted in old-text at start, replacing the 
             specified characters. new-text does not have to be the same length as length</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>String or Text</AISTypes>
		</Argument>  
		<Return><![CDATA[ 
	    <p>The result string after the replace has been done</p>
	    ]]></Return>
	</Syntax>
</Function>
