<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Function SYSTEM "../DTD/Function.dtd">
<Function>
	<KnowledgeBase>
        <Title>isEqual</Title>
		<FunctionName>isEqual</FunctionName>
		<FunctionType>Builtin</FunctionType>
    	<ArgumentTypes>Character String Symbol Vector BitVector ByteVector IntVector Complex ShortVector
                       FltVector ObjVector Structure Dictionary Directory Brick Void Function
                       Matrix NumMatrix Integer Float Number Complex Boolean Pair List Date </ArgumentTypes>    
        <DataType>String Structure ShortVector Dictionary Directory Vector Brick Complex NumMatrix Boolean Matrix Pair List Void Character Number Date Function FltVector IntVector NumVector ObjVector  BitVector</DataType>
		<RelatedFunctions>compareEQ comparison stringCiEQ substringCiEQ isIdentical</RelatedFunctions>
        <RelatedVMInstructions>vmregObjPointer vmregStringCompare vmregStringiCompare  </RelatedVMInstructions>
		<HumanKeywords>  Equal Analytic Object </HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
  <Description><![CDATA[ 
             <p> The <b>isEqual</b> function uses a case-sensitive comparison to determine if two objects are equal.  </p>
             <p> The <b>isEqual</b> function determines if the two object arguments of the same data type are equal . 
                 The resulting value is a Boolean value of true or false.   </p>
          ]]></Description>
	<Brief>
	   <Overview-String><![CDATA[
		<p>The <b>isEqual</b> function returns true if the argument <b>{obj1}</b> the argument 
        <b>{obj2}</b> are equal; otherwise false is returned. Two objects are considered equal 
        if they are the same type, each character value is the same, and the case is the same.
        </p>
        ]]></Overview-String>
        <Overview-Void><![CDATA[
		<p>The <b>isEqual</b> comparison function determines if two object  arguments are equal . 
           The resulting value is a Boolean value of true or false. The <b>isEqual</b> behaves 
           exactly like the <b>compareEQ</b> function. The #void constant will always be less than any other value.
        </p>
        ]]></Overview-Void>
        <Overview-Number><![CDATA[
		<p>The <b>isEqual</b> function returns true if its arguments are equivalent; otherwise false 
          is returned.  Two native objects are equivalent if they are equal after coercion.  
          Two compound objects are equal if they have the same type and if their individual 
          components are equivalent. 
        </p>
        ]]></Overview-Number>
        <Overview-Date><![CDATA[
		<p>The <b>isEqual</b> function returns true if its arguments are equivalent; otherwise false 
          is returned.  Two native objects are equivalent if they are equal after coercion.  
          Two compound objects are equal if they have the same type and if their individual 
          components are equivalent. 
        </p>
        ]]></Overview-Date>
        <Overview-Function><![CDATA[
		<p>The <b>isEqual</b> function returns true if its arguments are equivalent; otherwise false 
          is returned. When the arguments are both functions, the object ids of each function 
          will be compared. 
        </p>
        ]]></Overview-Function>
        <Overview><![CDATA[
		<p>The <b>isEqual</b> comparison function determines if two object  arguments are equal . 
           The resulting value is a Boolean value of true or false. The <b>isEqual</b> behaves 
           exactly like the <b>compareEQ</b> function
        </p>
        ]]></Overview>
        <Usage-String><![CDATA[
        <p>The <b>isEqual</b> function uses a case-sensitive comparison to determine if two 
         objects are equal.  An alternate method would be to use the <b>compareEQ</b> function 
         or the <b>=</b> function.  If  a case-insensitive comparison is desired, then the 
         <b>stringCiEQ</b> and <b>substringCiEQ</b> functions are available. 
        </p>
        ]]></Usage-String>
        <Usage-Number><![CDATA[
        <p>The <b>isEqual</b> function is used to determine if two Numbers are equal. 
        </p>
        ]]></Usage-Number>
        <Usage-Date><![CDATA[
        <p>The <b>isEqual</b> function is used to determine if two Dates are equal. 
        </p>
        ]]></Usage-Date>
        <Usage-Function><![CDATA[
        <p>The <b>isEqual</b> function is used to determine if two functions object 
           ids are equal. 
        </p>
        ]]></Usage-Function>
        <Usage-Complex><![CDATA[
        <p>The <b>isEqual</b> function is used to determine if two Complex Numbers are equal. 
        </p>
        ]]></Usage-Complex>
       <Usage><![CDATA[
        <p>The <b>isEqual</b> function when you wish to compare two object arguments and determine 
             if they are equal and you wish the result to be a Boolean.  The <b>isEqual</b> 
             function compares the keys and values of the two object arguments. Two objects are considered equal 
             if they are the same type, each character value is the same, and the case is the same.
        </p>
        ]]></Usage>
    </Brief>
	<Syntax>
	    <Expression><![CDATA[<p>   (isEqual  obj1 obj2) </p>]]></Expression>
		<Argument>
		  <Name>obj1</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p> An Analytic Object</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Character, String, Symbol, Vector, BitVector, ByteVector, IntVector, Void, Function
                       FltVector, ObjVector, Structure, Dictionary, Directory, Brick, Pair, List
                       Matrix, NumMatrix, ShortVector, Integer, Float, Number, Complex, Boolean, Date </AISTypes>
		</Argument>
    	<Argument> 
		  <Name>obj2</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p> An Analytic Object</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>Character, String, Symbol, Vector, BitVector, ByteVector, IntVector, Void, Function
                       FltVector, ObjVector, Structure, Dictionary, Directory,
Pair, List
                       Matrix, NumMatrix, Integer, Float, Number, Complex,ShortVector,  Boolean, Date </AISTypes>
		</Argument>
		<Return><![CDATA[
	    <p>If the obj1 and obj2 are of the same type and they are equal, a Boolean value 
           true is returned. Otherwise false is returned
        </p>
	    ]]></Return>
	</Syntax>
</Function>
