<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Function SYSTEM "../DTD/Function.dtd">
<Function>
	<KnowledgeBase>
        <Title>saveImmediate</Title>
		<FunctionName>saveImmediate</FunctionName>
		<FunctionType>Builtin</FunctionType>
        <ArgumentTypes>ObjectRepository Directory String</ArgumentTypes>
        <DataType> ObjectRepository</DataType>
	    <RelatedFunctions>isImmediate</RelatedFunctions>
        <RelatedVMInstructions> none </RelatedVMInstructions>
		<HumanKeywords>save repository index immediate boolean key pointer</HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
         <Description><![CDATA[
             <p> The <b>saveImmediate</b> function reads a value stored at the specified key, from the
              specified ObjectRepository and stores the new value  in the Repository Index.  </p>
          ]]></Description>
	<Brief>
	   <Overview><![CDATA[
		<p>The <b>saveImmediate</b> function reads a value stored at the specified key, <b>{key}</b>, 
        from the specified ObjectRepository <b>{aGor}</b> and stores the new value <b>{value}</b>
        in the Repository Index. </p>
        <p>The Repository Index is simply a Directory, which is saved on the disk with the Object Repository. The keys 
        in the Repository Index normally map to a value which is a pointer to the location in the
        disk file. Retrieving or Saving a value to the Object Repository is key driven and requires 
        two disk access: </p>
       <p><b>1) Load the Repository Index into the Virtual Memory of the Analytic Information Server 
          Server. </b></p>
       <p><b>2) Use the key and then the disk pointer associated with the key, read the value from 
           the disk. </b></p>
       <p>The <b>saveImmediate</b> function replaces the pointer value with the immediate value 
        from retrieved from the disk. Thus, if the Object Repository file is closed, the Repository 
        Index is saved in its modified state. If another Object Repository references causes the Object 
        Repository to be opened and the Repository Index to be loaded into virtual memory, the result of 
        the <b>saveImmediate</b> from the last reference is persists in the Repository Index. </p>
     <p></p>
       <IMG SRC="Image_saveImmediate.gif" >
      <p></p>
       ]]></Overview>
        <Usage><![CDATA[
        <p>The <b>saveImmediate</b> function should be used on values that are referenced many times 
       during an execution of an Lambda or function as it eliminates a disk access and will result in 
       optimized access times. The Repository Index will be dynamically resized to accommodate immediate 
        values and can grow to any size limited only by available virtual memory. </p>
        ]]></Usage>
    </Brief>
    <Syntax>
	    <Expression><![CDATA[<p>(saveImmediate aGor key value )   </p>]]></Expression>
		<Argument>
		  <Name>aGor</Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>The ObjectRepository which will be tested.</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>ObjectRepository</AISTypes>
		</Argument>    
		<Argument> 
		  <Name>key </Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>The key value associated with the object.</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>String</AISTypes>
		</Argument>
		<Argument> 
		  <Name>value </Name>
		  <Note><![CDATA[
		  <p>The value associated with the object.</p>
          ]]></Note>
		  <AISTypes>String</AISTypes>
		</Argument>
		<Return><![CDATA[
	    <p>The Object Id of the Object Repository.
        </p>
	    ]]></Return>
	</Syntax>
</Function>
