<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Essay SYSTEM "../DTD/Essay.dtd">
<Essay>
	<KnowledgeBase>
	    <Title>Undo Redo</Title>
		<Topic>Analytic Information Server</Topic>
		<SubTopic>User's Guide</SubTopic>
		<HumanKeywords>Development AIS Guide</HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
	<Section>
	    <Heading>6.1 Undo</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
			<h3>6.1.1 Overview</h3>
			All edit operations can be divided into three categories, move, insert, or delete.  Of these, insert
			and delete operations are saved in an ordered undo stack.  The last insert or delete operation can be undone by pressing
			Ctrl-Z even if the cursor has been moved around after the last insert or delete.  The next-to-last insert or
			delete operation can also be undone by pressing Ctrl-Z again and so on up to a limit
			of the maximum number of undo operations. This limit is a configurable parameter. For example:
			<ol>
				<li>InsertA.  Insert a sequence of chars.</li>
				<li>DeleteB.  Delete a char.</li>
				<li>Undo.  Undo DeleteB by inserting the deleted char back into the text.</li>
				<li>InsertC.  Insert a second sequence of chars.</li>
				<li>Undo.  Undo InsertC by deleting the second sequence of chars.</li>
				<li>Undo.  Undo InsertA by deleting the first sequence of chars.</li>
			</ol>
			<h3>6.1.2 Exceptions</h3>
			A few operations that cannot be be undone are not kept on the list. Operations that are not supported by undo are
			indent, unindent, comment, uncomment, tabify, and detab.		 
		  
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section>            
	<Section>
	    <Heading>6.2 Redo</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
			<p> A Ctrl-Y launches a &quot;redo&quot; operation which reverses the previous undo operation.  So, if undo deletes
			inserted text, redo re-inserts the text back into the text.  Similarly, if an undo inserts previously deleted text,
			the corresponding redo deletes the inserted text a second time.
			Note that only the last consecutive undo operations can be redone.  That is, the list of redo operations is reset
			if a new insert or delete operation is performed. So, in a sequence of operations such as undo, insert, undo, you
			can only redo the last undo.     </p>
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section>
</Essay>
