<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Essay SYSTEM "../DTD/Essay.dtd">
<Essay>
	<KnowledgeBase>
	    <Title>Editor Configuration</Title>
		<Topic>Analytic Information Server</Topic>
		<SubTopic>User's Guide</SubTopic>
		<HumanKeywords>Development AIS Guide</HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
	<Section>
	    <Heading>7.1 Initialization Files</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
			<p>
			<b>Overview.</b> The editor has two sets of parameters.  The non-configurable parameters are set by
			defined constants in the source code.  These parameters may be modified in the source.  Configuration
			parameters may be set by making changes to the source code or by editing the editor's initialization file.</p>
			<p>
			<b>Initialization Files.</b> One or two initialization files may be placed in the same folder as the
			folder containing the executable file, aised.exe.  The initialization files are named aisedver.ini and
			aised.ini.  The first is a release version distributed with each release of the editor and should not be modified.  The
			second initialization file is an optional user file that contains all the local overrides to the default settings
			provided in aisedver.ini.
			Put any changes to the settings in the release version that you wish to make.  Keep a change history noting
			the version number of the release and the date when each set of changes were made to this file (last change at
			the top of the history).</p>
			<p>
			<b>Updating the User Initialization File.</b>  The aised.ini file may be updated by noting the changes in
			the change history contained in the last release of the aisedver.ini file since the last release version shown
			in the change history of the aised.ini file:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>New Parameters.  If you wish to modify the setting for a new parameter, add a new entry with the
				modified value in the aised.ini file.</li>
				<li>New value.  If an existing parameter has a new default value, you may want to modify or remove an
				existing override in the aised.ini file.</li>
				<li>Deleted Parameter.  If a parameter is removed from the latest aisedver.ini file, remove any overrides
				in the aised.ini file.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>
			Update the latest version number in the change history of the aised.ini file and note the changes made.</p>
			<p>
			<b>Setting Parameters.</b>  When the editor starts execution, each parameter is set three times.   The
			parameters are set to the default values hard-coded into the executable.  If an aisedver.ini file can be
			located in the install directory, the default settings are overwritten by the settings in aisedver.ini.
			If an ais.ini file can be located in the install directory, the parameter settings are overwritten a second
			time with the values provided in the ais.ini file.</p>
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section>            
	<Section>
	    <Heading>7.2 Initialization File Format</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
			<p>
			<b>Comments.</b>
			An initialization file may contain zero or more lines consisting of comments, blank lines, and parameter settings.
			Comment lines begin with an octothorpe (#).  Comments are used for notes, a change history, and a description of
			each parameter.  The format of the description is:<br>
			ParameterName [Units]Default (Lower,Upper). Purpose<br>
			where: </p>
			<ul>
				<li>Units. Units stands for a unit of measure such as pixels or inches.  # is used to denote a count or a size.
				</li>
				<li>Default. Default stands for a default or nominal value.</li>
				<li>Lower,Upper. Lower,Upper stands for the range of acceptable values for this parameter.</li>
				<li>Purpose.  Purpose stands for a brief description of the role played by the parameter.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>
			<b>Parameter Name-Value Pairs</b>  A setting consists of a ParameterName, zero or more spaces, an
			equal sign, zero or more spaces, and a numeric value.  The parameter names in the ais.ini file should be
			the same as the names in the aisedver.ini file.  The values can be any value in the range specified.
			Only the name-value pairs that you wish to modify need to be added to the ais.ini file.</p>
			<p>
			<b>Configuration Parameters</b>  The current set of configurable parameters along with a description
			of each parameter may be found in the aisedver.ini file distributed with the executable file.</p>
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section>
</Essay>
