<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<!DOCTYPE Essay SYSTEM "../DTD/Essay.dtd">
<Essay>
	<KnowledgeBase>
	    <Title>Selected Text</Title>
		<Topic>Analytic Information Server</Topic>
		<SubTopic>User's Guide</SubTopic>
		<HumanKeywords>Development AIS Guide</HumanKeywords>
	</KnowledgeBase>
	<Section>
	    <Heading>4.1 Selecting Text</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
			<p>
			Anchor. Note that when text is first selected, an anchor is set at the current cursor position and then the cursor
			is moved to the new position.  The selected text from the anchor to the new cursor position is displayed with
			a dark blue background.  When extending a selected region, the cursor is moved to a new position. The selected text
			extends from the current anchor to the new cursor position.  The cursor may be in front of or after the anchor.</p>
			<p>
			Move. Text can be selected by clicking the mouse with the Shift key pressed or by dragging the cursor across a
			section of text.  Text can also be selected by almost any keyboard move operation by depressing the Shift key
			while carrying out a move operation.   The selected text can also be extended by repeating a move operation
			with the shift key depressed.  If text is currently selected, it is deselected by moving the cursor.</p>
			<p>
			Matching Parentheses.  If any pair of brackets are matched, the intervening text can be selected using
			Ctrl-S (for Select), including the brackets at both ends.  Paren matching must be enabled to use this mode
			of selection</p>
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section>           
	<Section>
	    <Heading>4.2 Operations on Selected Text</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
			<p>
			View edit operations involving selected text as a single operation that is carried out in two steps.  First
			some text is selected and then an operation is performed on the selected text.</p>
			<p>
			Insert. If text is currently selected, an insert operation will replace the selected text with the inserted
			characters.</p>
			<p>
			Delete. If text is currently selected, a delete operation will delete the selected text.  In the special case
			of Delete-Prev-Char and Delete-Next-Char, the selected text is deleted but no other characters are deleted.</p>
			<p>
			Clipboard. Selected text can be copied to the clipboard, appended to the clipboard, or moved to the clipboard.
			See the command summary in section 2.5 for more details.</p>
			<p>
			Indent and Comment.  Indent, unindent, comment and uncomment operations all require one or more rows of text
			to be selected.</p>
			<p>
			Dialogs.  The Find Dialog, Replace Dialog, and Set Tab Dialog utilize selected text to set the region to be
			operated on.  In addition, the Find Dialog and the Replace Dialog use selected text to mark the last text that
			has been matched or replaced.</p>
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section>   
	<Section>
	    <Heading>4.3 Preserving Selected Text</Heading>
		<Description><![CDATA[
			<p>
			Several edit operation preserve selected text.  They are Copy, Comment, Uncomment, Indent, Unindent, Tabify in
			the Tab Set Dialog,and Replace All in the Replace Dialog.  Except for the Copy operation, all of these
			operations modify the selected text.  So, the amount of selected text is always adjusted to extend from
			the beginning of the first row to the end of the last row after the modification to the text has been made.</p>
	    ]]></Description>
	</Section>
</Essay>
